Guide to the Washington Theater Club records, 1952-1983 MS2061
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Washington Theater Club records
1952-1983
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2061
116 Linear Feet
Collection contains correspondence, scripts, resumes, programs, administrative records, financial documents, photographs, art work, and audio cassettes from the Washington Theater Club, which was formed in 1957 to fill a perceived cultural void; to present good drama, away from Broadway; to speak out in plays of consequence; to present new ideas, new forms, and quality theater, which could be enjoyed and performed without racial barriers.. The materials date from 1952-83.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Hazel H. Wentworth, Executive Director and co-founder of the Washington Theater Club, donated these records in 1979.
Historical or Biographical Note
The Washington Theater Club was formed in 1957 to fill a perceived cultural void; to present good drama, away from Broadway; to speak out in plays of consequence; to present new ideas, new forms, and quality theater, which could be enjoyed and performed without racial barriers. The initial days of the Washington Theater Club were financially complex. John Wentworth had acquired a carriage house at 1632 0 St. N.W. in Georgetown, which had the essential space for a small intimate theater, with possible expansion potential. Zoning required that any theater venture be designated a private club. Even with a heavy input of money, Wentworth could not finance a professional theater and the building. The Washington Drama Center was organized to rent the building and pay for alterations to convert the space to a theater; and thereafter to provide professional theater, a drama school, and other activities.
Theater Venture I and Theater Venture II were developed to solicit funding to finance productions in 1960 and 1961. The Dramatic Arts Society of the District of Columbia was created to conduct a school and to produce and sponsor theatrical productions as a non-profit corporation, eligible to receive foundation and community support. The Washington Theater Club functioned with these support groups from 1957 to 1963, when it was incorporated as a non-profit theater and could stand alone. The designation "club" was necessary because of zoning problems resulting from the Club's location in a residential neighborhood adjacent to a church. The theater was, in actual fact, open to all with payment of nominal dues of $1.00.
As evidence of its growing success, the Washington Theater Club acquired a second location at 23rd and L Streets, N.W., which opened in 1970. The records of the Washington Theater Club reflect the progress of a regional theater from a small intimate dramatic venture to a full-fledged, highly acclaimed professional dramatic force operating at two locations, capable of successfully launching plays which had failed on Broadway, and effective in introducing new productions, new playwrights, and new performers. So successful was the club under the direction of Davey Marlin-Jones, that on April 11, 1969, it became the first theater in Washington to win the coveted Margo Jones award for persistence in a continuing program of new play productions. Its accomplishments included the production of ten world premieres, four American premieres, thirty Washington premieres, and the introduction of sixty-four writers new to area audiences.
Programs developed for dark Monday nights included staged readings of new plays to test feasibility for full production. Other programs included concerts by the Theater Chamber Players, who later became resident at the Kennedy Center, separate series of jazz concerts, dance, mime, and international events, as well as a showcase gallery in the lobby. The existing drama school, begun under the direction of the Wentworths, continued as a club activity to provide training for all ages and interaction with professional performers and directors. Like the theater production staff, Hazel Wentworth was motivated to expand the influence of the school to the disadvantaged, with outreach to Anacostia, a joint grant with Bowie State College, in-service training for college students on the east coast, and touring theater in the public schools and parks.
Like other performing arts groups which flourished in the sixties but did not survive the seventies, the Theater Club came to an end in 1974. Despite cash flow difficulties and a reliance on modestly-paid and volunteer staff, the Washington Theater Club was noted for its expansion into new areas and dramatic excellence from its modest inception in a 142-seat theater space to its two-house status with more than 9,000 subscribers.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains correspondence, scripts, resumes, programs, administrative records, financial documents, photographs, art work, and audio cassettes. The materials date from 1952-83. These records provide insight into many facets of theater management. There are extensive files of resumes for acting and support staff, of constant communication with Actors' Equity, League of Resident Theaters, and similar groups, materials related to funding and grant support, royalty negotiations, audition records, screening in large cities, and subscription and box office records. The collection also contains records related to the Board of Trustees.
Please note: the folder numbering is a mixture of an original numbering scheme and those a newer scheme designed by Special Collection staff. For this reason there may be times when the folder numbers may appear run consecutively. These numbers are simply used as a location guide and no material is missing and the material is in the correct order.
Hazel H. Wentworth, Executive Director and co-founder of the Washington Theater Club, donated these records in 1979.
Collection Organization
Organized into four series: Production files, Administrative files, General accounting, and Artwork, audio tapes, and record albums
Washington Theater Club; Theater; Audiocassettes; Performing arts; Hupper family; Photographs; Theater management; Washington (D.C.); Wentworth family; Wentworth,, Hazel H.; Ackerman family; Wentworth, John B.; Washington Theater Club (Organization: Washington, D.C.)
- Production files, 1960-1979; MS2061 Series 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains correspondence, flyers, brochures, newspaper and magazine articles, news releases, advertisements, programs, opening night lists, production staff worksheets, scripts, applications, and resumes. The material dates from 1960-79 with the bulk of the material falling within 1960-74.
  The first segment of the Production series contains Productions 1 to 90, arranged chronologically by numbered production. Within each file there are divisions with the following headings: programs, newspaper and magazines, advertisements, news releases, flyers and brochures, promotion- administrative, WTC extended (refers to productions whose runs were extended), production staff worksheets, opening night lists, art work, and cast background information.
  Non-Equity Productions 1 to 10 are filed with the same order strategy as the other major productions. Thereafter, Scripts 1 to 183 are arranged alphabetically by author, or by title, if no author is available. The scripts are of various types: some represent major productions; some were offered as Monday night readings; and many were never produced. Production numbers are provided as a cross reference to production files whenever possible.
  Correspondence and conclusions related to Script Reading for the years 1963-70 are filed after the Scripts section. Later script analysis was done by the Board of Trustees rather than the theater staff, and their efforts are filed with the Board materials under Playreading Committee. The next segment of the Production Series contains applications and resumes of actors, actresses, technical staff, managers, and directors. At the beginning of this segment are index files; one small collection on 3 x 5 cards with dates ranging from October 1972 to 1973, sorted by potential casting categories. Some similar cards of both types are scattered through the resume folders. In addition, ratings A - C, and/or numbers appear on some cards and resumes (presumably part of the organized audition process), as well as candid comments, negative and positive, to provide guidance in future casting.
  Applications and resumes with supporting documentation have been placed in one comprehensive alphabetical order, with papers for each application in the following order: resume; photograph; material such as brochures, press releases, letters of recommendation, and educational credentials; and correspondence. Multiple resumes for the same individual are arranged chronologically, to the extent possible with existing evidence.
  Within this series there were originally many folders grouped together and designated as "active", which, as directors changed, became "inactive." There were also resumes in mailing envelopes, never opened, as well as a few scripts, query letters, and personal correspondence, now relocated in appropriate series. Most files were not dated. For potential research value, original folders with significant headings have been retained, with a listing of prior contents on the folder or sheet of yellow paper which identified, them, and are arranged alphabetically at the end of the Resume file.
  The segment of the collection designated Special Events includes improvisational evenings, play productions by and for the Theater Club, staged readings of new plays, concerts by special groups, five years of performances by the Theater Chamber Players (a group which later became the resident company at the Kennedy Center), jazz concerts, dance programs, mime, and other special events. Arrangement within each folder conforms to the pattern established in the initial production series. Most of these events were presented on dark Monday evenings when the theater was not otherwise in use. Additional special productions will be found under Children's Theater Productions. The Children's Theater Production section contains shows produced in the Washington Theater Club training programs for children and teenagers, professional performances for young and family audiences (sponsored by the Theater Club), community outreach programs, and administrative material.
  - Production 1, The Matchmaker, Thornton Wilder., 1960 July 01-17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Production 2, A Hatful of Rain, Michael Gazzo., 1960 July 09-31 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Production 3, The Lesson & The Chairs, Eugene Ionesco., 1960 August 02-14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Production 4, A Clearing in the Woods, Arthur Laurents., 1960 August 16-28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Production 5, Cry of the Raindrop, Lonny Chapman --programs, 1961 June 06-18 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Production 5--newspaper and magazine, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Production 5--news releases, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Production 5--flyer and brochures, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Production 5--promotion - administrative, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Production 5--art work, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Production 5--cast background information, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Production 6, Tevya and his Daughters, Arnold Perl--programs, 1961 June 22-August 06 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Production 6--newspaper and magazine, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Production 6--advertisements, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Production 6--news releases, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Production 6--promotion - administrative, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Production 6--art work, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Production 7, Call Me By My Rightful Name, Michael Shurtleff. --programs, 1961 July 11-23 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Production 7--newspaper and magazine, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Production 7--advertisements, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Production 7--news releases, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Production 7--flyers and brochures, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Production 7--promotion - administrative, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Production 7--art work, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Production 8, A Country Scandal, Anton Chekhov --programs, 1962 February 27-March 19 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Production 8--newspaper and magazine, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Production 8--news releases, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Production 8--promotion - administrative, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Production 8--production staff worksheets, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Production 8--art work, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Production 9, Legend of Sarah, James Gow and Arnold Usseau.--programs, 1962 April 23-05 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Production 9--newspaper and magazine, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Production 9--news releases, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Production 9--flyers and brochures, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Production 9--promotion - administrative, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Production 9--art work, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Production 10, The Glass Menagerie, Tennessee Williams. --programs, 1962 April 10-May 06 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Production 10--newspaper and magazine, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Production 10--news releases, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Production 10--flyers and brochures, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Production 10--promotion - administrative, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Production 10--opening night lists, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Production 10--art work, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Production 11, Three at 9:30: The Rising of the Moon, Lady Gregory; A True Story, Mark Twain; and The High School, Sholom Aleichem., 1962 May 12-27 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Production 11--programs, --newspaper and magazine, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Production 11--news releases, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Production 11--flyers and brochures, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Production 11--promotion - administrative, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Production 11--art work, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Production 11--cast background information, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Production 12, Period of Adjustment, Tennessee Williams., 1962 June 05-August 26 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Production 12--programs, --newspaper and magazine, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Production 12--advertisements, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Production 12--news releases, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Production 12--flyers and brochures, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Production 12--promotion - administrative, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Production 12--WTC extended, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Production 12--opening night lists, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Production 12--art work, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Production 12--cast background information, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Production 13, The Establishment, Peter Cook., 1962 December 04-1963 January 13 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Production 13--programs, --newspaper and magazine, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Production 13--advertisements, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Production 13--news releases, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Production 13--flyers and brochures, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Production 13--promotion - administrative, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Production 13--WTC extended, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Production 13--art work, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Production 14, Brecht on Brecht, translated by George Tabort--programs, 1963 February 27-April 13 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Production 14--newspaper and magazine, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Production 14--advertisements, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Production 14--news releases, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Production 14--flyers and brochures, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Production 14--promotion - administrative, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Production 14--WTC extended, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Production 14--production staff worksheets, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Production 14--art work, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Production 15--The Blacks, Jean Genet. --programs., 1964 September 29-October 03 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Production 15--newspaper and magazine 80 --advertisements, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Production 15--news releases, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Production 15--flyers and brochures, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Production 15--promotion - administrative, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Production 15--art work, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Production 16--The Amorous Flea - Based on Molier's "School for Wives".--programs, 1964 October 27-November 15 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Production 16--newspaper and magazine, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Production 16--advertisements, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Production 16--news releases, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Production 16--flyer and brochures, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Production 16--promotion - administrative, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Production 16--art work, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Production 17--Return of the Runaway, Mary Leckie. --programs., 1964 December 01-13 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Production 17--newspaper and magazine, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Production 17--advertisements, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Production 17--news releases, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Production 17--flyer and brochures, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Production 17--promotion - administrative, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Production 17--art work, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Production 17--cast background information, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Production 18--The Blood Knot, Artholl Fugard. --programs., 1965 January 05-31 (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Production 18--newspaper and magazine, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Production 18--advertisements, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - Production 18--promotion - administrative, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - Production 18--art work, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - Production 19--The Bernard Shaw Story, Bramwell Fletcher. --programs., 1965 February 16-28 (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - Production 19--newspaper and magazine, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - Production 19--advertisements, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - Production 19--news releases, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - Production 19--flyers and brochures, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - Production 19--promotion - administrative, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 110)
  - Production 19--production staff worksheets, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 111)
  - Production 19--art work, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 112)
  - Production 20--The Deadly Game, James Yaffe. --programs., 1965 April 02-21 (Box 3, Folder 113)
  - Production 20--newspaper and magazine, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - Production 20--advertisements, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - Production 20--news releases, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 116)
  - Production 20--flyers and brochures, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 117)
  - Production 20--promotion - administrative, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 118)
  - Production 20--art work, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 119)
  - Production 21, A Touch of the Poet, Eugene O'Neill. --programs., 1965 April 17-30 (Box 3, Folder 120)
  - Production 21--newspaper and magazine, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 121)
  - Production 21--advertisements, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 122)
  - Production 21--news releases, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 123)
  - Production 21--promotion - administrative, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 124)
  - Production 21--art work, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 125)
  - Production 22, The Tempest, William Shakespeare. --programs., 1965 April 21-May 16 (Box 3, Folder 126)
  - Production 22--newspaper and magazine, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 127)
  - Production 22--advertisements, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 128)
  - Production 22--news releases, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 129)
  - Production 22--flyers and brochures, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 130)
  - Production 22--promotion - administrative, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 131)
  - Production 22--opening night lists, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 132)
  - Production 22--art work, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 133)
  - Production 22--cast background information, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 134)
  - Production 23, Slow Dance on the Killing Ground, William Hanley.--programs, 1965 October 14-November 07 (Box 4, Folder 135)
  - Production 23--newspaper and magazine, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 136)
  - Production 23--advertisements, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 137)
  - Production 23--news releases, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 138)
  - Production 23--flyers and brochures, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 139)
  - Production 23--promotion - administrative, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 140)
  - Production 23--art work, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 141)
  - Production 23--cast background information, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 142)
  - Production 24, U.S.A., Paul Shyre and John Dos Passos.--programs, 1965 November 10-December 05 (Box 4, Folder 143)
  - Production 24--newspaper and magazine, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 144)
  - Production 24--advertisements, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 145)
  - Production 24--news releases, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 146)
  - Production 24--flyers and brochures, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 147)
  - Production 24--promotion - administrative, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 148)
  - Production 24--WTC extended, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 149)
  - Production 24--art work, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 150)
  - Production 25, Ernest in Love, Lee Pockriss and Anne Croswell.--programs, 1965 December 21-1966 January 23 (Box 4, Folder 151)
  - Production 25--newspaper and magazine, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 152)
  - Production 25--advertisements, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 153)
  - Production 25--news releases, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 154)
  - Production 25--flyers and borchures, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 155)
  - Production 25--promotion - administrative, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 156)
  - Production 25--art work, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 157)
  - Production 26, Romeo and Jeannete, Jean Anouilh --programs, 1966 January 27-February 20 (Box 4, Folder 158)
  - Production 26--newspaper and magazine, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 159)
  - Production 26--advertisements, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 160)
  - Production 26--flyers and brochures, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 161)
  - Production 26--promotion - administrative, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 162)
  - Production 26--production staff worksheets, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 163)
  - Production 26--art work, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 164)
  - Production 27, The Typists and The Tiger, Murray Schisgal. --programs, 1966 February 24-April 20 (Box 4, Folder 165)
  - Production 27--newspaper and magazine, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 166)
  - Production 27--advertisements, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 167)
  - Production 27--news releases, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 168)
  - Production 27--flyers and brochures, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 169)
  - Production 27--promotion - administrative, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 170)
  - Production 27--art work, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 171)
  - Production 28, The Birthday Party, Harold Pinter.--programs, 1966 March 24-April 16 (Box 4, Folder 172)
  - Production 28--newspaper and magazine, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 173)
  - Production 28--advertisements, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 174)
  - Production 28--news releases, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 175)
  - Production 28--flyers and brochures, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 176)
  - Production 28--promotion - administrative, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 177)
  - Production 28--art work, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 178)
  - Production 29, The Eccentricities of a Nightingale, Tennessee Williams. --programs, 1966 April 20-May 15 (Box 4, Folder 179)
  - Production 29--newspaper and magazine, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 180)
  - Production 29--advertisements, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 181)
  - Production 29--news releases, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 182)
  - Production 29--flyers and brochures, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 183)
  - Production 29--promotion - administrative, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 184)
  - Production 29--art work, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 185)
  - Production 30, Spread Eagle, Russel Baker and others. --programs., 1966 May 19-June 26 (Box 5, Folder 186)
  - Production 30--newspaper and magazine, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 187)
  - Production 30--advertisements, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 188)
  - Production 30--news releases, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 189)